all right what's going on guys in this
video I'm going to be taking you through
some minimalistic workouts that'll take
you under 45 minutes per session so this
is a 2-day per week routine however if
you have more training days available
than that I'll also explain how you can
modify these two workouts into a 3-day
per week 4 day per week or 5day per week
schedule so everything you need to know
to set up your own minimalistic training
split will be laid out in this video and
throughout these workouts we'll be
applying many of the fundamental
minimalist training principles that I
discussed in my last video which I'll
link Down Below in case you missed it
all right let's get started with full
body day one so after 2 to 3 minutes of
brisk walking on the treadmill and a few
dynamic stretches just a few arm swings
and a few leg swings is fine we're
kicking things off with two sets of flat
dumbbell press the first set will be a
heavy set for four to six reps and the
second set will be a lighter back off
set for 8 to 10 reps so we'll get our
strength set in first and then do our
hypertrophy set now there are two
reasons why we're doing a dumbbell press
rather than a barbell press on a
minimalist routine first dumbbells are
generally more time efficient because
you don't need to load and unload any
plates which does chew up some time and
second dumbbells allow for a greater
range of motion than the barbell this
normally isn't a big deal because we can
compensate for the barbells minor
limitation by also including a stretch
focused exercise like a cable fly
however on a minimalist routine we're
trying to minimize the number of
exercises we do so in this case it makes
more sense to choose a pressing exercise
that also provides a large stretch on
the pecs so a dumbbell press or a dip
would probably be your best options now
from a technique standpoint point I
recommend lowering the dumbbells down
with a slight elbow tuck at around 30 to
45° when viewed from the top and then as
I press I'll flare my elbows out if you
feel any shoulder discomfort when you
flare it's fine to just keep your elbows
tucked the entire time okay after that
we're moving on to the dumbbell Romanian
deadlift for two sets of 8 to 10 reps
again I'm going for the dumbbells here
mainly because they tend to be a bit
more time efficient but the biomechanics
of the exercise will be the same whether
you use dumbbells or a barbell the main
thing to keep in mind with the RDL is to
Simply push your butt back as you allow
the weight to drop straight down under
control don't think about lowering the
weight to touch the floor simply set
your hips back and let the dumbbells
naturally lower in a straight line
reversing the motion once you feel a big
stretch in your hamstrings without
allowing your lower back to round I like
to maintain a nice smooth Cadence on
these where I don't fully lock out at
the top and this helps me keep tension
on my hamstrings however if you did want
to activate the glutes a bit more you
could lock the hips at the top and
squeeze your glutes together I'd also
strongly recommend using straps for
these so that your grip strength doesn't
limit the amount of tension your
hamstrings receive next we're doing a
two grip lap pull down for two sets of
10 to 12 reps using a different grip for
each set so for the first set we're
doing a overhand middle grip to Target
the midback and the lats and then on the
second set we're doing a underhand close
grip to Target the biceps a bit more and
to hit the lats from a slightly
different angle then after the second
set to get a little more bicep work you
can strip the weight back and do some
overhead curls this way we'll make sure
the high threshold bicep fibers
experience a high level of muscular
tension as well okay after that we're
moving on to a single working set of 8
to 10 reps per leg on the dumbbell step
up this will be our main quad and glute
Focus movement for the day now one thing
to remember about minimalistic training
is that because we're often only doing
one single set for some exercises it's
very important that we execute that set
as perfectly as possible in this case we
want to be forcing our front leg to
carry all the load so minimize cheating
with your back leg as much as possible
and remember that it's just there for
keeping balance I prefer to work each
leg one leg at a time because that way
you're not losing tension in between
reps which can really drag the set out
another thing you may notice is that you
need to go heavier than you think most
people stop well shy of failure on
step-ups and lunges so to get to failure
or at least within one rep of failure
you'll probably need heavier weights
than you'd normally use and again using
straps is smart since they'll prevent
your grip strength from being a limiting
factor up next we've got one set of 12
to 15 reps plus a drop set on the
overhead cable tricep extension the
reason I'm going with an overhead tricep
extension rather than a regular press
down is that the tri ceps will already
be hit in a more neutral shoulder
position with the flat dumbbell press so
it'd be a bit more redundant to also hit
them with a press down also a new 2022
study from mayo and colleagues found
that overhead tricep extensions resulted
in about 40% more hypertrophy compared
to regular press Downs even when volume
matched which is pretty huge now there's
been quite a lot of noise about this
study online some people claim that the
results are most likely a fluke however
according to the mass research review it
was a very well-designed study and there
are at least three plausible
explanations for why overhead extensions
led to substantially more muscle growth
than press Downs so while I wouldn't put
too much stock in a single study like
this if you are limited on time and can
only fit in one tricep isolation
movement I would favor a overhead tricep
extension more than press Downs okay so
for these you want to lock your elbow in
place with the cable just behind your
head squeeze your triceps to move the
weight and then lower the weight back
down under control and try to feel a
nice big stretch at the bottom after
reaching failure once I'll drop the
weight back by about 30 to 40% and then
take the triceps to failure once again
okay after that we've got one set of 12
to 15 reps plus another drop set on the
machine lateral raise I personally use
this Atlantis standing lateral raise
machine at my gym mostly because I find
I can get a much larger range of motion
here while maintaining consistent
tension on my side delts however if you
don't have this machine you can use a
seated machine option or a cable machine
or even dumbbells as long as you're
taking the muscle to failure with good
form the fibers will be maximally
recruited regardless also strap in again
here so I can use only my side delts to
sweep the weight out as opposed to
relying on my grip and more specifically
my thumb to support the weight again I
use a larger than usual ROM on these but
if that ROM isn't comfortable for you
you can just stop at 90° so parallel to
the floor and again as long as you're
taking the set to failure the total
activation level will be very similar
and again after reaching failure I'll
drop the weight by 30 to 40% and go to
failure again to really finish the
fibers off and get in a little extra
volume without killing too much time by
doing a whole other set okay and to
finish off the First full body day of
the week we're doing one set of 12 to 15
reps on the horizontal tow press for the
calves now doing calf raises on a leg
press machine is the exact same basic
movement pattern is doing them on a
standing calf raise machine because on
both exercises your leg is straight Not
Bent however when you're seated your
upper body doesn't have to bear any of
the load so I find that I'm able to get
a better mind muscle connection with my
calves when I do calf raises on a seated
leg press machine and once again after
reaching failure I'll drop the weight
back by 30 to 40% and go to failure
again one thing to keep in mind with the
calves is to make sure you don't start
bouncing on the drop set reps a lot of
people have a tendency to let loose once
fatigue starts setting in but you'll get
the most out of the set if you keep your
form locked in and remember each and
every rep should have a nice 1 second or
so pause at the bottom and a full
squeeze at the top okay let's jump into
full body day two on the second day
we're kicking things off with the hack
squat doing one heavy top set for four
to six reps and then one lighter back
off set for 8 to 10 reps now the reason
I'm going for the hack squat is because
on a minimalist routine you can often
get away with less warm-up sets on
machines than on free weight compound
exercises for example with barbell back
squats it'll sometimes take me a half an
hour just to get all my warm-up sets
done whereas with the hack squat I'll
just hit two maybe three quick warm-up
sets and then I'm doing my working sets
within 5 or 10 minutes tops so for the
first heavy top set I'm choosing a
weight that'll have me about one rep shy
of failure so an RP of nine for four to
six reps and here I'm just focusing on
moving the weight I'm thinking about
driving through my heels while
maintaining consistent pressure against
the shoulder pads and after the first
heavy set I'll rest for about 3 minutes
and then for the back off set I'll drop
the weight back and this time focus a
little more on controlling the negative
and feeling my quads working this is
more of the hypertrophy set so I'm
focusing more on the Mind muscle
connection rather than just moving the
weight and on both sets I'm getting to
full depth and purposefully allowing my
knees to come forward past my toes which
is perfectly safe and I can link another
video on that down below okay after that
we're doing an antagonistic super set
for the chest and back now an
antagonistic set is when you train two
opposing muscle groups back to back
without rest and I'm a big fan of these
because one muscle will be working while
the other is resting so in this case
we're doing two sets of a high incline
Smith machine press to Target the pecs
shoulders and triceps and then we're
super setting that with a tar row to hit
the mid traps lats rear delts and to
some extent the biceps with the incline
press I'm setting the bench angle a bit
higher than usual so around 45 to 60°
and I'm doing that so the delts get more
involved rather than doing both both a
vertical press and a horizontal press we
just meeting in the Middle with a high
incline press to save on time and this
will do a good job of hitting the pecs
and the shoulders with a single movement
we're also taking a slightly closer grip
so we can take the triceps through a
greater range of motion and this will
shift some of the emphasis to the upper
pecs as well which is a weak point for
most people then we're super setting
this with 10 to 12 reps on the tar row
now my jy's tar row machine is right
next to the Smith machine so I can
superet these two easily but if your gym
has these two machines further apart
instead you can just flip around on the
bench grab some dumbbells and do some
chest supported incline dumbbell rows
instead of tar rows for the same sets
and Reps now when doing tar rows I'll
usually do one set with a wider grip and
one set with a closer grip just to
Target the back from slightly different
angles and I should also point out that
even though we are super setting I'll
still rest for about 30 seconds to a
minute in between the two exercises so
just because you're super setting and
you're going back and forth doesn't mean
you need to go straight to the other
exercise getting a little rest in
between to catch your breath is a good
idea so in practice the superet will
look something more like this which
still saves on time but allows me to
recuperate more in between super sets
all right after that we're moving on to
one set of 10 to 12 reps on the seated
hamstring curl plus a drop set a recent
2020 study showed greater hamstrings
growth with seated leg curls overlying
leg curls across a 12we training study
so if we're given the option to do only
one I pretty much always favor seated
leg curls these days and because this
difference seems to be related to the
higher degree of stretch you get on the
ham strings with the seated variation
I'll accentuate this effect by leaning
forward over the machine throughout the
set and then since we're only doing one
set here we're taking it all the way to
failure and then dropping the weight
back by 30 to 40% and going to failure
again then we're doing one set of 12 to
15 reps on the Easy Bar bicep curl plus
some myor reps again just one allout set
to failure here so we want to make sure
we execute that set as perfectly as
possible so I'm focusing on curling the
weight out and up not just up and
thinking about driving through my pinky
to Q for supination as I curl I'm also
thinking about squeezing my biceps to
move the weight and keeping a looser
grip on the bar so that my forearms
don't take over after hitting failure
with good technique we're doing some myo
reps to enhance the set further rather
than a drop set this time so this time
we're going to keep the weight the same
and instead of dropping the weight back
we'll simply rest for 3 to 4 seconds and
then do another four reps then we'll
rest for another 3 to four seconds and
do another four reps and we'll just keep
doing that until we can no longer get
four reps at that point the set is done
now the good thing about myor reps is
that they allow you to get in a lot more
high tension reps in a short period of
time remember that it isn't until near
the very end of a set the Reps become
maximally hypertrophic so by doing these
myor rep mini sets where the muscle is
already very close to failure you're
essentially cutting out any of those
early low tension reps and jumping
straight to the more effective stuff all
right and to finish off the workout
we're doing one set of cable crunches
for 12 to 15 reps plus a double drop set
so I like to do these kneeling with the
Rope locked in over my head and then
I'll crunch down hard on my abs and
allow my entire back to round including
my lower back after reaching failure
once I'll drop the weight back by about
30% and then go to failure again and
then to really finish things off we'll
do one more drop set this time so I'll
strip it back another 20 to 30% and then
go to failure one last time now if you
guys were wondering how you could adapt
this to a three four or 5 day per week
program this is how I would do it you'd
keep most of the exercises sets and Reps
the same but simply modify how you'd
split up your volume throughout the week
if you want to train three days a week
i' do the same full body workout number
one and then split the second full body
day up into a upper body day and a lower
body day you could also add a little
more volume to the upper lower Days by
either adding an extra set for some of
these exercises or you could add a few
extra exercises for your individual week
points on those days if you want to
train four days a week you just split up
both full body workouts into two
separate upper lower days so you'd go
upper lower rest upper lower rest rest
and again you can add some volume to
these workouts if you find them to be a
bit too short and if you want to train 5
days a week you could do the same basic
thing but this time with an upper lower
Push Pull leg split done 5 days per week
or if you want to have all this work
done for you you can check out my new
12we Essentials program which just
launched this week over on Jeff ner.me
this one guys thank you so much for
watching don't forget to leave me a
thumbs up if you enjoyed the video
subscribe if you haven't already and
I'll see you guys all here in the next
one